Register of the Ralph Haswell Lutz Papers, 1903-1963
Hoover Institution Archives
Ralph Haswell Lutz Papers,
1903-1963
68039
Lutz, Ralph Haswell, 1886-1968
12 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes. (5.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, notes, and diaries, relating to administration of the Hoover Institution, teaching of history and international relations at Stanford University, and various aspects of European history during World War I and the interwar period.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Access Points
World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Austria.; World War, 1914-1918--Germany.; World War, 1914-1918--Italy.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; Austria.; Germany.; Germany--History--Revolution, 1918.; Germany--History--1918-1933.; Italy.; Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace.; Stanford University.; Education.
Biographical Note
1886, May 18 Born, Circleville, Ohio
1906 A.B., Stanford University
1910 Ph.D., University of Heidelberg
1916-20 Assistant Professor of History, University of Washington
1919 Member of Team Gathering Material for Hoover War Collection in Europe
1920-25 Co-director, Hoover War Collections, Stanford University
1925-43 Chairman of Board of Directors, Hoover War Library, Stanford University
1934 Editor, The Causes of the German Collapse in 1918
1935 Editor, The Treaty of St. Germain, A Documentary History of Its Teritorial and Political Clauses
1942 Editor, The Blockade of Germany After the Armistice, 1918-1919
1943 Editor, Organization of American Relief in Europe, 1918-1919
1966 Editor, The Political Institutions of the German Revolution, 1918-1919
Container List
Original Accession
- RESEARCH FILES
  - Austrian Peace Delegation, 1919. (Box 1.)
    - Selected Documents
  - Causes of the German Collapse in 1918. Published by Stanford University Press, 1934.
    - Notes
    - Miscellaneous Documents
  - "Imperial Germany in Revolution, 1918-1919, A Documentary Survey," by Charles B. Burdick and Ralph H. Lutz. Unpublished.
    - Drafts of Title Page and Preface
    - Outlines
    - Notes and Miscellaneous Lists of Documents
    - Chronology of Events
    - Source Materials (Translations of Selected Published and Unpublished German Documents)
      - Group I. List of Documents by Folder Number:
        - Documents, Folder 1, #1-63 (Box 2.)
        - Documents, Folder 2
        - Documents, Folder 2A, #64-125
        - Documents, Folder 3, #125-217
        - Documents, Folder 4, #218-285
        - Documents, Folder 5, #286-327
        - Documents, Folder 6 (Missing)
        - Documents, Folder 7, #378-427
        - Documents, Folder 8 (Missing)
        - Documents, Folder 9 (Missing)
        - Documents, Folder 10, #506-545
        - Documents, Folder 11, #546-610
        - Documents, Folder 12, #611-657
        - Documents, Folder 13, #658-698
        - Documents, Folder 14, #699-754
        - Documents, Folder 15, #755-812
        - Documents, Folder 16 (Missing)
      - Group II. List of Documents by Folder Number: (Box 3.)
        - Documents, Folders 1-5A
        - Documents, Folders 6-11B (Box 4.)
        - Documents, Folders 12-18 (Box 5.)
        - Documents, Folder 19 (Missing)
        - Documents, Folders 20-21
        - Documents, Folders 22-29 (Missing)
        - Documents, Folder 30
        - Documents, Folders 31-35 (Box 6.)
        - Documents, Folder 36 (Missing)
        - Documents, Folders 37-38
      - Group III
        - Unarranged Documents
        - Unarranged Documents (Box 7-9.)
  - Italian Politics, 1914-1919 (Box 9.)
    - Translation of Aldrovandi, by Jean Black
    - Translation of Pietro Bertolini's Diary, by Jean Black
    - Translation of The Intervention of Italy, In the Secret Documents of the Entente, by Jean Black
  - Memorandum of Conversation between Professor Singer of Vienna and R. H. Lutz in November 1926, about German-Austrian relations.
  - Nazis and the Bruening Ministry.
    Translations of Selected Documents
  - Raymond Poincoré Letter to R. H. Lutz, 1926, about the Austrian Ultimatum to Serbia of July 1914.
Increments
- WRITINGS
  - "The Spanish Armada"; thesis by Ralph N. Lutz, 1903 (Box 10.)
- MISCELLANEA
  - Correspondence between Ralph H. Lutz and his father Harry E. Lutz (trip reports) (Box 10.)
  - Letters and reports from E.D. Adams pertaining to A.R.A. Euopean operations
  - Letters from E.L. Harris regarding the deposition of his papers at the Hoover Institution
  - Letters from Frank A. Golder
  - Letters from German publishers and collectors
  - Correspondence between H. Hoover and Henry L. Stimson concerning the "Green Smear" (size of the American overseas army)
  - Copies of documents dealing with the criminal case against F.K. Ferenz and the "Friends of Progress" in Sacramento (accused of being pro-nazi), 1942
  - Notes, passports, clippings, maps, etc.
  - "The State of France in 1791," Thesis, Stanford University, 1904, by Ralph H. Lutz.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, etc.
  - Diaries and notebooks (16) for the time between 1918 and 1943 (Box 11.)
  - "Report of Mr. S. Miles Bouton Concerning the Conditions in Germany," 1919
  - Letters and clippings regarding Professor Lutz' acceptance of a German merit cross (Verdienstkreuz) of the Order of the German Eagle, conferred upon him and other Americans by the Leader and Chancellor of the German Reich, Adolf Hitler, 1938.
  - "Transcript of the Cornerstone Ceremony of the Franklin D. Roosevelt Library, Inc., at Hyde Park, New York." Sunday, Nov. 19, 1939. (Copy for Ralph H. Lutz).
  - Letter of Harold H. Fisher to Ralph H. Lutz, dated August 8, 1945
  - Army commission orders, Headquarters of the U.S. Military Mission in Berlin, 1919